A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director, Simon Flexner, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2 FA138
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director, Simon Flexner, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2
1903-1935
Rockefeller Archive Center
Smith, Edric Brooks
Norris, James U.
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Flexner, Simon
FA138
2.64 Cubic Feet 6 boxes
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Custodial History note
Received 28 January 1985: Photocopy of Table of Contents to Simon Flexner Papers at the American Philosophical Society Library, 129 pp. In 3-ring binder notebook.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 301-2
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Medical research; Medical sciences; Vivisection; Operations management; Medicine, Preventive; Life sciences; Biology -- Research; Smith, Edric Brooks; Norris, James U.; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Flexner, Simon
- Administrative correspondence, 1903-1935; 2; 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a few items written to Emmett L. Holt and to James U. Norris, but mainly administrative correspondence with and through the hands of the Business Manager. Mainly items dealing with affairs of the Institute including antivivisection campaigns, appointments, buildings and landscaping, distribution of Salvarsan, publications (Journal of Experimental Medicine, Monographs), purchases and development of New York City and Princeton properties; exemptions from draft for certain laboratory workers, salaries and personnel matters. Some correspondence with others on the Board of Scientific Directors or employees.
  Many handwritten notes and notations to Edric B. Smith while abroad or away for summer months. Several handwritten notes from Mrs. Flexner. Including reprint from Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences v. 60, no. 14, Dec. 1925 of Memorial to Abraham Jacobi written by Simon Flexner. Also includes publicity speech, Triumphs of Experimental Medicine, delivered January 27, 1933 over station WJZ, by Simon Flexner.
  Non-routine items under the following dates.
  Arrangement note
  Partially arranged with additions.
  Arranged in chronological order. 1903-1919 (Box 1); 1920-1925 (Box 2); 1926-1935 (Box 3)
  - 1903-1919 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with C. W. Stiles on investigation and treatment of Hookworm in Southern states, with Aug. 12, 1914 copy of letter from J. D. Rockefeller completing 5-year grant to Sanitary Commission, 1909 January 9-29
    - Copy of confirmation of check from John D. Rockefeller for Professor Ehrlich in the amount of ten thousand dollars deposited in the Lincoln National Bank, 1909 July 20
    - Jerome Greene appointed Curator to meet regulations to secure free entry of alcohol for scientific purposes, 1910 October 27
    - Carbon copy of letter to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. regarding painting brought by Alexis Carrel from France, 1917 February 8
    - Attached to correspondence of January 1920 with F. A. Dickey regarding routine to be followed in sending application blanks, 1919 October
  - 1920-1925 (Box 2)
    - To Simon Flexner — outline of work plan by Wade H. Brown, 1920 May 12
    - Report to Business Manager from S. G. O'Rourke, "Need for a Waiting Room", 1920 October 15
    - Copy of circular letter as written by T. Mitchell Prudden requesting Trustee authorization for purchase of radium, 1920 November 9
    - Correspondence with Ernest H. Starling, University of London regarding hardships of Dr. Pavlov and possibilities of Institute assistance, 1921 February 8
    - Copy of letter from Dr. James MacKenzie, St. Andrews Institute, St. Andrews, 1921 April 7
    - From T. M. Prudden for John D. Rockefeller, Jr. a recollection of the first organizational meetings of The RIMS, 1922 January 5
    - Notice distributed to Associated Press and United Press and New York Times on Anniversary reception given by Mrs. Simon Flexner celebrating founding of RIMR, 1922 January 20
    - Handwritten letter from Simon Flexner covering letter sent to Scientific Directors regarding DeKruif articles, 1922 October (?)
    - Correspondence with editor of McClures Magazine regarding article on Tryparsamide, 1923 September-October
    - Correspondence concerning decision not to reappoint Dr. Harry W. Graybill, 1923 October-December
    - Correspondence between Winthrop W. Aldrich and Simon Flexner on amendment to BY-Laws regarding Board of Trustees appointments, 1924 March 7-31
    - Correspondence with Francis W. Peabody regarding his appointment to Board of Scientific Directors, 1924 March 19
    - Thank you letter for book by Mungo Park from John D. Rockefeller Jr. to Simon Flexner, 1924 June 4
    - Copy of letter to Theobald Smith from Simon Flexner hoping he will not decide to retire on 65th birthday, 1924 June 11
    - Further correspondence between Winthrop Aldrich and Simon Flexner regarding amendment to By-Laws to clarify method of selection of members of Board of Trustees, 1924 September 26
    - Group of handwritten undated notes from Simon Flexner to Edric B. Smith, 1925
    - Correspondence while travelling abroad between Simon Flexner and Edric B. Smith dealing with Institute affairs, 1925 January-August
    - Includes some earlier letters also regarding invitation to A. N. Richards of University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine to spend a year at Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1925 June 5
    - Includes letters as early as January 1924 from Ida H. Hyde to Simon Flexner asking advice in regard to making bequests, 1925 September 28
  - 1926-1935 (Box 3)
    - Final letter of arrangement for visit of Professor F. Neufeld from Berlin with correspondence dating back to Oct. 21, 1924, 1926 February 11
    - Memorandum from E.B. Smith to Simon Flexner: information on opening dates or occupation dates of various Institute buildings, 1926 March 30
    - Handwritten note from Simon Flexner with clipping regarding gas stove explosion, 1926 April 7
    - Letter from Mayor's secretary to Simon Flexner asking if he would serve on Commission of City Planning and Survey, 1926 May 13
    - Series of propositions forming basis of plan for Institute work in physics and biophysics. Signed by Simon Flexner, Ralph W. G. Wyckoff and Harry Clark, 1926 December 21
    - File of correspondence Nov. 16, 1926-June 5, 1927 between Abraham Flexner (for General Education Board) Simon Flexner and Francis Peabody regarding a grant to Soma Weiss, 1927 April 7
    - Handwritten letter from Simon Flexner to E.B. Smith regarding plans for change of direction in Institute's cancer research, 1928 March 8
    - Handwritten letter from E.B. Smith to Simon Flexner with first intimation of Mr. Debevoise ideas of possible concessions to City of New York to achieve agreement on closing of 68th Street, 1928 July 10
    - Handwritten note to be typed from Simon Flexner to George E. Vincent of Rockefeller Foundation on Dr. Sabin's stature as scientist, 1929 May 20
    - Handwritten note to E.B. Smith from Simon Flexner about interview with President 2/27/30, 1930 February 20
    - Handwritten letter from S. Flexner to E.B. Smith regarding budget item to propose to Trustees so that Dr. Rous will receive compensation to serve as assistant to S. Flexner — informally, 1930 May 19
    - Letter from Simon Flexner, written from Union Memorial Hospital, Baltimore where he was hospitalized for "no serious illness", 1930 May 20
    - With correspondence from June 24, 1930 with handwritten letter from T. M. Lowry regarding meeting of Faraday Society, 1930 July 8
    - Clipping from New York Medical Week. Announcement of award of William Wood Gerhard Medal to Simon Flexner, 1931 January 1
    - Handwritten note from Simon Flexner to E.B. Smith about Noguchi mementos and bust, 1931 June 30
    - Letter from Earl B. McKinley, Dean of George Washington School of Medicine regarding people to be selected as advisors on Leonard Wood Memorial for the Eradication of Leprosy, 1932 May 13
      Includes reply.
  - Correspondence between Dr. Flexner and E.B. Smith, Business Manager, 1903-1919 1928 and posthumous; 5 folders
    Between 1934 when Simon Flexner planned his retirement as Director of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research until 1940 Dr Flexner kept an office at the Institute where he worked on a biography of William Henry Welch. Box 4 consists of correspondence between Dr. Flexner and E. B. Smith, Business Manager who saw to the collection of material, financial arrangements for the support of the writing and many other details. After 1940 when Simon Flexner gave up his office at the Institute many details were still handled through Mr. Smith until Dr. Flexner' s death in 1946 when the Institute was involved in details of newspaper notices, funeral preparations and finally in the Memorial Service held 12 June 1946.
    Folders 1-4 arranged in chronological order.
    - 1934 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Memorandum on By-Law changes dealing with changes in pension plans and copies of correspondence with W. J. V. Osterhout on changes in his pension plan, 1934, January 27
      - Lewis H. Weed (Johns Hopkins University) to Simon Flexner asking recommendation for continued Foundation support of History of Medicine Institute under Sigerist, 1934, February 1
      - E.B. Smith to Simon Flexner in Cairo description of Theobald Smith funeral Service, 1934, December 14
    - 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Herbert S. Gasser to Simon Flexner and reply, (1935-1936) November 21, 25
        Simon Flexner to remain as one of the editors of JOURNAL OF EXPERIMENTAL MEDICINE.
    - 1937 May 3, 5 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Request for information by Simon Flexner regarding an early request from McGill University for financial aid. Reply from EBS that excerpts from Minutes of 13 June 1907 and 12 Oct. 1907 referring to request. Statement from Welch to Gates found in Welch papers, (1937-1946) 1937 May 3, 5
    - Posthumous to 1957 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1946 June 12
        Includes copy of pamphlet issued publishing the addresses made at the Memorial meeting.
    - 1903-1919 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Letter to Dr. Holt, Mr. Norris, Mr. Green and Mr. James, 1903-1919; 41 Letters mostly handwritten
        These were selected from the files by Mr. E.B. Smith, for their historical value when Dr. Flexner was working on his history of Dr. Welch.
        The letters mainly deal with Institute business when Dr. Flexner was abroad or away on vacation or while hospitalized for illness and the business manager at the time handled matters and informed Dr. Flexner.
  - Correspondence between Simon Flexner and Waldo Flinn, 1928-1944 (Box 5)
    Between 1928 and 1944 Waldo Flinn was assistant to Business Manager Edric B. Smith. Under his direct supervision were matters of personnel involving non-scientific staff; publications; the administrative operation of the various support services and various other duties involving the care and maintenance of the laboratories.
    Special mention is made only of special interest items.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1928-1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 1916 pamphlet included "Special Investigation of poliomyelitis, 1916" a report to the Mayor of New York City Aug. 12, 1928, 1928-1929
        Copy of a statement made to the press about poliomyelitis.
    - 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Includes correspondence about space requirements for the Swiss mice colonies for the International Health Board, 1930-1931
        December 10, 1931 definition of the designation "Fellow" as used at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.
    - 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Continues correspondence about increasing needs for animal housing with several handwritten letters from Conrad Hon and problems in avoiding infection among the animal colonies, 1932-1933
      - Correspondence about procedures in the preparation of animal media and prices for same, 1932 October-November
      - Mimeograph copy of address delivered by Simon Flexner over WJZ, New York City. "Triumphs of Experimental Medicine", 1933 January 27
      - Correspondence National Research Council, Simon Flexner, Waldo Flinn and statements from Research Corporation and Massachusetts Institute of Technology exploring the question of granting of patents for discoveries in medical research and how best to insure the public good, 1933 November-December
      - Correspondences regarding outbreaks of rabbit-pox in Brown/Pearce rabbit colony including plans for isolation to prevent spread, 1933 December
    - 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence between Simon Flexner and Waldo Flinn which extends into retirement and time when Dr. Flexner was writing the biography of Dr. Welch, 1933-1934
  - Funeral and obituary material (Box 5, Folder 5 and 6)
    - Press material; typescript copies of addresses made by Homer Swift and Raymond Fosdick at funeral service, 1946 May 4 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper articles, obituaries and editorials. Obituary articles from (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Académie des sciences, 1946 May 27
      - SCIENCE 107 (1948) p. 611-613
      - Obituary notices of Fellows of The Royal Society 6 (1949) 409-445
      - JOURNAL OF EXPERIMENTAL MEDICINE 85 frontispiece, 1947
      - LA PRESSE MEDICALE 34 (l946) 495, 1946
      - BULLETIN de L'ACADEMIE DE MEDECINE 24-25-26 (1946) 429
      - ARCHIVES OF PATHOLOGY 42 (l946) 234-242, 1946
      - JOURNAL OF IMMUNOLOGY 54 (1946) i-vii
      - JOURNAL AMERCIAN MEDICAL ASSOCIATION 131 (1946) 171
    - Copy of photograph used in press notices (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Memorial Service, 1946 June 12 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Typescript of addresses (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Lists of invitees (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Posthumous correspondence and bibliography (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Addition to the collection, 17 circa 3" folders
  From papers found in inactive files of the RU Corporate Secretary/Faculty Administrator, received February 1987 from Ms. Lila J. Magie.
  - Biographical materials (Box 6)
    - Curriculum vitae, with revised/updated versions (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Dinner in honor of Simon Flexner, Hotel Ambassador. Program, seating arrangements, 1924 December 13 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Obituaries, clippings (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and subject files (Box 6)
    - Berg, Hilda von, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Gasser, Herbert S., 1935-1949
      - Gasser, Herbert S., 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Gasser, Herbert S., 1937-1944 1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Osten, Anna von der, 1935-1945
      - circa 1935-1936 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - 1936 May-June (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - 1936 July (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 1936 September-November (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 1937-1941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Translation of Erinnerungen, Gedanken, und Meinungen des Dr. B. Naunyn, 1925, J.F. Bergmann, München, pp. 125-128 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Rockefeller Foundation. Duplicated typescripts re 'Vital Process' program. Statement by Simon Flexner, 19 Nov 1934; copies of letters by Walter B. Cannon, 21 Nov 1934; H. D. Dakin, 20 Nov 1934; W. H. Howell, addendum, undated; Frank R. Lille, 20 Nov 1934, 1934 November (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Spahlinger cure" for tuberculosis, 1921-1935 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Correspondence re method devised by Henri Spahlinger and RIMR publicity, 1921-1924; clippings, 1921-1935.
    - Tittmann, Harold H. Inquiry re reminiscence of 1921 meeting with Abraham or Simon Flexner, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Includes index cards with records of SF addresses/lectures ca 1920-35 and appointments, 1925-37 (honorary); receipts, miscellaneous correspondence.